Guide to the Helen Edmonds Papers, 1951-1994 RL.00352
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Helen Edmonds papers
1951-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edmonds, Helen G. (Helen Grey), 1911-1995
RL.00352
4.4 Linear Feet
circa 4,000 Items
Collection contains primarily correspondence and printed materials, including speeches, clippings, and photocopies. Two large sections of materials concern Edmonds' interests and activities as a member of the Republican Party and her work as an alternate delegate to the U.N. General Assembly, 1970. Some materials relate to her work with the National Peace Corps Advisory Council, to educational exchange, consultations in Europe and Israel, and other work experiences in an international context. Papers representing her duties as a college professor are limited.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Helen Edmonds Papers were donated to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library on November 9, 1981.
Biographical Note
Helen Edmonds was a historian, scholar, and civic leader. She was the first African American woman to earn a doctorate from Ohio State University, the first to become a graduate school dean, and the first to second the nomination of a United States presidential candidate.
Born in Lawrenceville, VA, Edmonds received her bachelor’s degree in history from Morgan State College in 1933. She went on to receive an M.A. in History at Ohio State University in 1938, followed by a Ph.D. from that same institution in 1946. Edmond's dissertation was published in 1951 as her first book, The Negro and Fusion Politics in North Carolina, 1894-1901. Edmonds also published numerous articles in scholarly journals on politics in the South. Her second book, Black Faces in High Places, was published in 1971.
In 1941 Edmonds joined the faculty of North Carolina College, now North Carolina Central University, where she remained until her retirement in 1977. During her tenure at NCCU, Edmonds taught U.S. and European diplomatic history, served as chair of the department of history, Dean of the Graduate School, and University Distinguished Professor. After her retirement from the teaching faculty in 1977, she became a member of the Board of Trustees.
Edmonds was appointed by the U.S. Department of State as a Leader-Specialist in International Education Exchange in 1954. Through this post she helped develop educational exchanges for U.S. faculty and students in Germany, Austria, Denmark, Sweden, and France. She also served as a visiting instructor in numerous institutions in the United States, Europe, Africa, and the Middle East including Harvard University, the Massachusetts Institute for Technology (MIT), the Free University of Berlin, the University of Stockholm, Ohio State University, and the University of Liberia.
An active Republican, Edmonds seconded the nomination of President Dwight D. Eisenhower at the Republican National Convention in San Francisco in 1956. During the second term of the Eisenhower Administration she traveled throughout Africa promoting American ideals and values in colonies that were soon-to-be independent nations. In 1970, President Richard M. Nixon appointed Edmonds as an alternate delegate to the United Nations General Assembly where she chaired the Human Rights Committee.
Edmonds also held important leadership roles in civic organizations such as the United Negro College Fund, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Legal Defense Fund, the United Research and Development Corporation, the National Council of Negro Women, and Delta Sigma Theta Sorority. She was the fifth president of the African American women's service organization, the Links.
In 1986 Edmonds was named a Distinguished Woman of North Carolina. Three years later the North Carolina Central University social science and history building was renamed in her honor. Edmonds died in Durham, North Carolina on May 9, 1995.
Chronology
1911 Dec. 3 Born in Lawrenceville, Va.
1933 Graduated from Morgan State University
1938 Earned Master's Degree from Ohio State University
1941-1977 Professor at North Carolina Central University
1995 Died in Durham, North Carolina
Collection Overview
Collection contains primarily correspondence and printed materials, including speeches, clippings, and photocopies. Two large sections of materials concern Edmonds' interests and activities as a member of the Republican Party and her work as an alternate delegate to the U.N. General Assembly, 1970. Some materials relate to her work with the National Peace Corps Advisory Council, to educational exchange, consultations in Europe and Israel, and other work experiences in an international context. Papers representing her duties as a college professor are limited.
Educational exchanges; African Americans -- Politics and government; African Americans -- Correspondence; Historians -- United States; African American college teachers -- North Carolina -- Durham; African American historians; United Nations. General Assembly; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ) -- History -- 20th century; Edmonds, Helen G. (Helen Grey), 1911-1995; Peace Corps (U.S.) -- Management
- Alphabetical Series
  - Addresses: (Box 1)
    - 1956-1974 (Box 1)
    - Europe: American University Women, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Germany, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Material, 1911- (Box 1)
  - Clippings:
    - 1956-1982, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - China, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Mt. Carmel Symposium), 1971 (Box 1)
  - Germany, 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - Israel: Mt. Carmel Symposium, etc., 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - Lecture Tour:
    - Europe Lecture and Seminar Materials, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - Denmark, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Sweden, 1957 (Box 1)
  - The National Links, Inc., 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - The North Carolina Historical Commission, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Peace Corps. National Advisory Council, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Photographs. Europe Leader Specialist, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Political Material:
    - Addresses, etc., Republican National Committee, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - Addresses, Reports, Memoranda etc., of the Republican National Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - Governor's Inaugural Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - N.C. Republican Party, 1951-1976 (Box 1)
    - Personal Notes, etc., used by Dr. Edmonds for Campaign Speeches, 1956 (Box 1)
  - President's Committee on Government:
    - Contracts, Minority (Box 1)
    - Community Resources Conference, 1958, Jan. 15 (Box 1)
  - Printed Material: General, 1956-1970 (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series
  - Alternate Delegate of the 25th Session of the United Nations General Assembly, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - European, 1954-1958 (Box 1)
  - General, 1951-1981, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Germany, West - Post-Doctoral Study and Research, 1954-1956 (Box 2)
  - Republican National Committee:
    - 1953-1956 (Box 2)
    - Expense Accounts and Itineraries, undated (Box 2)
  - Republican National Committee. Letters from Rank and File persons during and following Dr. Edmonds' Campaign Tour, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Republican National Committee, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Republican Party, 1958-1976, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - White House, and the Executive Department of the U.S. Government, 1952-1976, 5 folders (Box 2)
- United Nations Series
  - General Assembly. Fifth Committee: Budget and Personnel, 1970, Nov. 9, Dec. 16 (Box 2)
  - General Assembly. Third Committee:
    - Addresses and Reports of Prof. Edmonds and others, and Research on Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Budget and Personnel, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Clippings re: Professor Edmonds, 1970 (Box 2)
    - The Elderly and the Aged, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Freedom of Information, 1951-1970 (Box 2)
    - High Commissioner for Human Rights, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Housing, Building, and Planning, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - International Covenant on Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights, and on Civil and Political Rights, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Narcotics, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Natural Disasters, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Nazism and Racial Intolerance, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Prisoners of War; Armed Conflict, 1969-1970, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Provisional Summary Record, 1970, Sept. 25-Dec. 15, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Racial Discrimination, Elimination of, 1970. (Box 3)
    - Religious Intolerance, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Trade and Development, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - General Assembly:
    - Economic and Social Council, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - High Commissioner for Human Rights, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
    - High Commissioner for Refugees, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Human Rights and Scientific and Technological Developments, 1970, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Israeli and Arab Question, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Outer Space. Peaceful Uses of, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Peace-keeping and the International Court of Justice, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Racial Discrimination. Report of the Secretary General, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Report to Samuel De Palma by Professor Edmonds, 1971, Feb. 18 (Box 3)
    - Sea-Bed and the Ocean Floor, Use for Peaceful Purposes Only, undated (Box 4)
    - 25th Session:
      - Notes and Memoranda of Professor Edmonds, 1970 (Box 4)
      - U.S. Representatives; Biographical Information of Dr. Edmonds, 1970 (Box 4)
    - War Criminals, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Work of the Organization and Agenda, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Youth and Education, 1970, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Related Activities of Professor Edmonds, 1971 (Box 4)
  - U.S. Arms Control and Disarmament Agency: Social Science Advisory Board, 1972 (Box 4)
- Printed Materials Series
  - Programs and Invitations, 1939-1977 and undated, 7 folders (Box 4)
- Oversize Materials
  - Alphabetical Series
    - Clippings, 1956-1982, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Clippings, China, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Lecture Tour. Sweden, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Political Material. Personal Notes, etc., Used by Dr. Edmonds for Campaign Speeches, 1956 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence Series
    - European, 1954-1958 (Box 5)
    - White House and the Executive Department of the U.S. Government, 1970-1976 (Box 5)
  - United Nations Series
    - General Assembly. Third Committee:
      - Clippings about Professor Edmonds, 1970 (Box 5)
      - Nazism and Racial Intolerance, 1970 (Box 5)
      - Prisoners of War. Armed Conflict, 1970 (Box 5)
      - Racial Discrimination, Elimination of, 1970 (Box 5)
    - General Assembly:
      - Trade and Development, 1969-1970 (Box 5)
      - Israeli-Arab Question, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Printed Material
    - Programs and Invitations, 1939-1977, and undated, 7 folders (Box 5)